(soft gentle music)
- No country on Earth
has more military bases
abroad than the United States,
with bases in places like
the Caribbean, the Azores,
then countless ones all over Europe,
stretching into the Arabian
Peninsula to Kenya and Africa.
Diego Garcia in the Indian Ocean,
Singapore in Southeast Asia, to Australia,
and dozens of bases in Japan and Korea.
In total, the US operates bases
in more than 70 countries
spanning the entire globe
and is able to project
power virtually everywhere.
But there is one base
that is completely
different from all of them
because usually these bases
are in allied countries
with which the US has good relations
and military cooperation.
But not this one.
The US base in Cuba.
It is called Guantanamo Bay,
and unlike the other bases,
this one is located in a country
that the US is in conflict with.
The US considers Cuba a
state sponsor of terrorism,
and Cuba considers the US
presence in their country illegal.
(light pulsing music)
The base is a place of extreme contrast.
Some parts of it look so much
like a typical American city,
and a pretty nice one, actually.
There are schools, sports fields.
There's a McDonald's where
you can "liberate your day"
by eating a McMuffin.
And then there are these
suburban-style houses
where US military personnel can live.
There's even a somewhat
makeshift nine-hole golf course
right on the base.
The greens, little islands
surrounded by the dirt.
- I'd have to say this is probably
the strangest course I've played.
It is very challenging.
- But right next to this
seemingly typical American town,
there are large detention camps
housing some of the US's
highest-security prisoners,
camps that have caused political
controversy over decades.
For this extensive documentary,
I set myself the goal to
understand this unique place
because Guantanamo Bay
plays an important role
that goes far beyond the headlines
during the War on Terror.
This is America's most
controversial base, explained.
So here's the deal.
I'm building up to
something with this video.
Throughout this story,
I will be trying to view Guantanamo Bay
as a sort of metaphor
because I believe that this military base
can represent the complicated relationship
between the United States
and the rest of the world.
And I've chosen four
themes to guide this idea.
First, there is independence,
a word that means so much in
how the US defines itself,
but also how it views its
ties with other nations,
and independence is the perfect keyword
to lead us to our first question.
How did the US acquire this piece of land
in the first place, and why
is there a US base in Cuba?
(light thoughtful music)
The answer, not surprisingly, is by force,
but not by war with Cuba,
but instead with Spain.
Christopher Columbus had
claimed Cuba for Spain in 1492,
and for centuries it was
part of the Spanish Empire,
which at its largest extent
stretched all across the Americas.
But in the late 1800s,
the Spanish hold had
significantly decreased,
and Cuba and Puerto Rico
remained the last Spanish
holds in the region.
Cubans began to fight for independence,
and for years, the United
States watched on the sidelines
until they couldn't anymore.
(light pulsing music)
Disturbing reports began making their way
into the US news cycle.
Cuban rebels fighting for independence
were getting support from local
farmers who provided housing
and food to the resistance fighters.
And to put a stop to this,
Spain decides to move anyone
who lives in the countryside
into literal concentration camps.
Anyone who refuses to relocate
to these camps is killed,
and within these camps,
diseases and starvation quickly spread.
Hundreds of thousands of
Cubans die in these camps,
and the American public
becomes sympathetic
as they hear more horror stories
about what their neighbors across the Gulf
are being subjected to,
and they begin to ask their
government to step in.
The pressure from the American public
and the desire to push the last remnants
of European powers out of the Americas
finally leads to the United
States joining the fight.
Just a little over 120 years earlier,
the US had fought its
own war for independence,
but now it is helping Cuba do the same.
The war doesn't last long after this.
Spain agrees to give up its
last remaining colonies,
and suddenly, Cuba is freed.
(gentle contemplative music)
Except, actually, it isn't.
The treaty between the
United States and Spain
guarantees the independence of Cuba,
but it allows the US to occupy the island.
In turn, the US makes clear to Cuba
that it will only withdraw its troops
if Cuba agrees to its own
treaty with the United States,
a treaty that includes
leasing land to the US
for a naval station,
the very one that would
become Guantanamo Bay.
Cuba, in no position to negotiate,
has little choice but to
agree, and the lease is signed.
A lease that has no expiration date
and can only be terminated
if both countries agree.
(gentle thoughtful music)
With the Guantanamo Bay
Naval Base established,
the United States begins sending
annual payments for the lease to Cuba
in the amount of $2,000
paid in gold coins,
and the US establishes a
permanent camp on the island.
They build housing for military personnel,
and they even built a baseball field.
The US has fought for Cuban freedom,
but it made sure
that it can shape what
that freedom looks like,
and it will not take long
until the relationship
changes drastically.
(tense uneasy music)
With Cuba now left to its own devices,
a series of various presidents
and dictators rule the country,
leading up to US-backed
dictator Fulgencio Batista.
Here he is with US President Eisenhower.
For the US, the situation
couldn't be much better.
Guantanamo Bay becomes an important port
for the United States
Navy and the Caribbean.
In 1931, a grass runway
is set up by the bay.
A decade later, that runway is paved,
and another runway is built
on the other side of the bay,
which is eventually extended
so it can accommodate newer jet aircraft.
- [News Reporter] On the
southeast coast of Cuba,
Guantanamo's commodious
and well-sheltered harbor
can accommodate the entire US fleet.
- The base's presence
is tolerated by Cuba;
after all, it even helps their economy,
with thousands of workers
crossing the border to the base every day.
- [News Reporter] 1,200
United States Marines
are sailing aboard the
Army transport Barnett
for winter training in Guantanamo, Cuba.
US Devil Dogs off to
safeguard our new outposts.
- However, after just a few
decades of peaceful coexistence,
everything changes.
In 1959, Fidel Castro
successfully overthrows
Batista's dictatorship,
and he installs a new communist regime,
one that quickly becomes very friendly
with the Soviet Union,
the arch-nemesis to the United States.
And with that, the Cold War
between these two superpowers
has reached Guantanamo Bay.
- [News Reporter] Castro
marks the second anniversary
of his revolution with the
biggest military parade
ever staged in Cuba.
President Eisenhower broke
off diplomatic relations
with the message read by
Press Secretary Haggerty.
- Meanwhile, our sympathy
goes out to the people of Cuba
now suffering under
the yoke of a dictator.
- After decades of
toleration for the base,
Cuba's new leader, Castro,
has a very clear demand.
He wants the land back for Cuba.
Since, according to the treaty,
both countries need to agree
and war against the powerful
United States is not an option,
there is little Castro can do,
except perhaps turn to the Soviet Union.
Strengthening this new
alliance might offer protection
and, just maybe, enough leverage
to push the Americans out.
For the typical American,
the tensions between the United
States and the Soviet Union
had so far only been felt
far away from home turf,
proxy wars in Asia
with American and Soviet forces
supporting opposite sides,
and heavy militarization in Europe.
But Cuba's alliance with the
Soviet Union changes this.
Suddenly, the Cold War was just
90 miles away from Florida.
As the iron curtain is
placed down in Europe
in the form of walls and fences,
another iron curtain rises
just outside the border of Guantanamo Bay.
Except this one is made of cactus.
Cuban troops are deployed
to plant a large cactus strip
around the American base.
(lively orchestral music)
- [News Reporter] The Cubans have planted
a cactus curtain strip around the base.
75 feet wide, it's a vigorous plant,
as effective as a wire fence.
Looking at the base today,
you can see the outline right here,
and then you see a second
perimeter around it
on the Cuban side.
The term "cactus curtain"
is used to this day
to describe the border between the base
and the rest of Cuba.
But the cactus border
was just the beginning,
because both the Cuban and
the American militaries
planned an even deadlier
deterrent: landmines.
Around 55,000 mines are
placed in this strip,
making it one of the largest
minefields of its time.
With tension so high,
it feels like it's only a matter of time
before something drastic happens.
And so it does.
(tense uneasy music)
In response to the United States
placing nuclear missiles
in Italy and Turkey,
where they are clearly within
the reach of the Soviet Union,
the Soviet Union now does the same,
and it stations its own
nuclear missiles in Cuba.
The US publishes a series of photos
showing these missile bases in Cuba,
and the situation escalates.
- The presence of these large, long-range,
and clearly offensive weapons
of sudden mass destruction
constitutes an explicit
threat to the peace
and security of all the Americas.
To halt this offensive buildup,
a strict quarantine on all
offensive military equipment
under shipment to Cuba is being initiated.
- [News Reporter] The US
threw up a steel fence,
prepared to stop any vessel
carrying materials of war.
- [Host] Both the US and the Soviet Union
are now within striking
distance of each other,
and nuclear war seems
closer than ever before.
Immediately, alarms ring out
through the base of Guantanamo Bay,
ordering all civilians to evacuate.
- [News Reporter] Over
3,000 Navy and Marine
wives and children are
evacuated from Guantanamo.
- With little time, pets are left behind,
and each person carries only
one suitcase of belongings,
not knowing if they will ever be able
to return to their homes again.
The evacuees join the world
as everyone watches and waits,
until at last everyone can
finally breathe easy once again.
- [News Reporter] Soviet
Chairman Khrushchev
decided to dismantle the bases in Cuba
and to remove the offensive weapons.
The missiles that had threatened the US
went back where they came from.
- The Soviet Union agreed to
take its missiles out of Cuba
in exchange for the United States to agree
not to attack or invade Cuba,
as well as a secret deal
to also remove its missiles from Turkey.
(bright thoughtful music)
Though the immediate crisis is over
and civilians are able
to return to their homes,
not everything is back to normal.
Castro still wants the base gone,
and he starts to reject the checks
that the United States
has been sending regularly
to pay for the lease.
He also shuts down a pipeline
that supplies the base with fresh water.
Castro offers to supply
one hour of water per day
for humanitarian needs, but
not anymore beyond that.
This offer is rejected by the Americans.
Instead, tanker ships filled with water
are sent to Guantanamo
while workers construct
a desalination plant.
To this day, the base has to operate
autonomous from the rest of Cuba.
Ocean water is turned into drinking water
by two desalination plants.
Electricity comes from
a diesel generator plant
as well as from wind turbines
that were installed in 2002,
and supplies are shipped
in from the United States.
(lively string music)
To this day, Cuba has rejected
every US lease payment
since the Castro family's
leadership began,
and that choice to stay
even when unwelcome
is not unique to Guantanamo
but can be seen as a constant
in how the US tries to
build global presence,
as no other country on Earth
maintains such a vast military
footprint around the globe.
And the challenges the United
States faces at Guantanamo Bay
are often the very same it
struggles with on a larger scale.
This same pattern also
shows up in the next chapter
of the base: immigration.
(gentle contemplative music)
In 1991, just a stone's throw
away from Guantanamo Bay,
unrest in Haiti ramps up.
The Haitian president
was overthrown by a military dictatorship,
and now thousands of Haitians are fleeing
using makeshift rafts, many
of whom are intercepted
by the US Coast Guard and
sent to Guantanamo Bay,
as the base soon becomes
the symbol of the crisis.
- [News Reporter] The
US Coast Guard planes
and ships sighting several
hundred bodies so far.
Number of survivors isn't
known, but it isn't large.
- The US classifies the fleeing Haitians
as economic migrants, requiring
them to undergo screening
to determine if they qualify for asylum.
And in order to carry out this process
without bringing them onto US soil,
Guantanamo Bay becomes the base
where their cases are reviewed.
The camp grows quickly,
with thousands of Haitians
packed into a space
never meant to hold them.
The old airfield is turned
into a sprawling tent city,
one that soon grew enormously,
as visible by these satellite pictures.
And even this space was not enough.
The golf course nearby
was repurposed as well
to become a temporary tent city.
The base soon reaches maximum capacity,
and the decision is made that
anyone else encountered at sea
will skip processing altogether
and is forcibly sent back to Haiti.
- [News Reporter] They fled
Haiti in hope of a better life.
They're returning now
in fear of their lives.
- As for those that did
make it to Guantanamo,
they don't fare much better.
Inside the perimeter, life is hard.
Trash piles up, and food is
often unevenly distributed
as overcrowding strains the
water and electricity supply.
Even still, throughout this
period between 1991 and 1995,
many at Guantanamo did their best
to improve the living
conditions of the refugees.
- We've had complaints of the food,
and it did look pretty dismal to us.
- It is dismal.
I will make no apologies for the fact
that the food is not good; it isn't good.
As we get more food in, we will
start to vary the menu more,
but right now, the
complaints are legitimate.
- But with a situation thrust upon them
with little logistical support
from the US government,
they simply have to make
do with limited funding
and resources.
The residents of each small camp
got to elect their own camp leaders,
who in turn meet regularly
with the generals
to discuss possible improvements.
Following these meetings,
residents are given more autonomy,
for example, having a say in
meal planning and preparation.
And inside the camps, the
military police patrol unarmed,
carrying only a radio,
a sign both of the residents' peacefulness
and of an effort to appear
less like prison guards
and more like peacekeepers.
But the frustration
that the individual
service members can't ease
comes from the fact that
the camp's residents
receive no answers about
what will happen next.
And even the military itself
must wait on the White House.
Life in these refugee
camps was extremely hard.
Rows of cots stretch
out on concrete slabs,
sometimes laying directly in the dirt,
and if someone causes trouble,
they are taken to a different location.
Roughly 4 1/2 miles east of the airfield,
a makeshift jail is built.
Its name is Camp X-Ray.
You can see the fencing around it
as well as multiple watchtowers
encircling the camp.
From this view, it might
appear that these roofs
belong to buildings housing the prisoners,
but that is not what they are.
This footage from 2021
shows the by-now abandoned
Camp X-Ray from the ground.
As you can see when we zoom in,
the roofs mostly cover cages
where prisoners are kept,
there are no walls,
and the prisoners are
exposed to the elements
with no privacy.
(light thoughtful music)
But these people at Camp X-Ray
were not the only ones
separated from the main camp;
going south, there is yet
another camp being built:
Camp Bulkeley.
The early '90s was a time during which
a new fear began spreading like wildfire.
Fear of HIV.
The spread of the epidemic
led the American Center for
Disease Control and Prevention
to falsely label Haitians
as a group with increased
risk for contracting HIV.
And because of this label,
Haitians are screened much more intensely
than any other nationality for the virus,
with every Haitian national
required to undergo testing.
And if someone does test
positive in Guantanamo Bay,
they are removed from
the general population
and sent to Camp Bulkeley,
and the refugees are given bracelets
that they are required to wear,
identifying them as carriers of HIV.
Out of over 20,000 Haitians,
a total of 276 people
are ultimately quarantined
in Camp Bulkeley,
with little access to proper healthcare,
and with their fate also unknown.
These people are all individuals
who have passed a screening
to be granted asylum to the United States.
But a 1987 law prohibits anyone with HIV
from entering the country.
This puts them into legal limbo.
And when asked by an AP reporter
why they cannot enter the US,
a spokesperson for the US Immigration
and Naturalization Service replied,
"They're going to die
anyway, aren't they?"
Weeks turn into months,
which turns into years,
and after two years have passed,
the Haitians imprisoned in Camp Bulkeley
still don't know their fate,
until finally a US federal
court rules that Camp Bulkeley
is essentially an HIV prison camp,
and it orders those living
there to be evacuated.
Within half a year, Camp
Bulkeley's residents
are granted entry to the United States,
and the camp officially closes.
As for the rest of the Haitians
waiting in Guantanamo Bay,
they are soon joined by a
different group of refugees,
as yet another crisis
led to a second influx
of people on the base.
This time from Cuba itself.
After the fall of the Soviet Union,
Cuba slipped into an economic
crisis, sparking protests
with people demanding
better living conditions
and political change.
In 1994, this led to a massive
surge in attempts by Cubans
to reach Florida on makeshift rafts.
Those who managed to make
it to the United States
were offered legal asylum,
and at its peak, as many as 33,000 people
set out on this journey.
In response, the Clinton administration
began taking action to stop it
and decides that any
rafters intercepted at sea
will also be taken to Guantanamo,
adding even more stress
to the already overcrowded refugee camp.
- [News Reporter] Guantanamo
Bay is filling fast.
Yesterday alone, a record 2,300 rafters
were plucked from the Straits
of Florida and brought here.
- [Host] Eventually, the
Clinton administration
even goes so far to change policy.
While it used to be that any
Cuban rescued on the waters
by the US Coast Guard would
get to enter the United States,
under the new policy,
only those who actually make it to Florida
with their self-made rafts get to stay;
everyone else will be sent back to Cuba.
- [News Reporter] Picking
up those Cuban rafters,
still putting out to sea for America,
and then doing what would've
been unthinkable before this,
pulling into port in still communist Cuba
and handing those refugees
back to Castro's police,
something America's
never ever done before.
(gentle contemplative music)
- [Host] For the Cubans
already at Guantanamo, though,
a lengthy legal and
political battle took place
to decide their fate
as well as the fate of
the Haitian refugees.
At one point during this time,
a couple of Cuban detainees
managed to escape from their camp,
and they occupy a church on the base
located right next to the McDonald's.
These Cubans were eventually brought back,
and the area was cordoned
off by the military.
But the situation led to this
fascinating photo being taken.
The McDonald's at Guantanamo
Bay, surrounded by barbed wire,
a photo that became a powerful symbol
of the base's contradictions.
In 1995, after years of
turmoil and waiting in limbo,
the refugees can finally leave Guantanamo,
and all of the camps are closed.
By the mid-'90s, Guantanamo
had become a symbol
of how the United States
handles immigration,
a reflection of a system that even today
remains one of the country's most divisive
and unresolved issues.
- Given the nature of
this country politically,
do you have any hope that
this immigration question
is gonna get resolved within
this decade, Senator Simpson?
- I really do.
- [Host] And the use of the
base as a place to hold migrants
has only recently
returned to the headlines
as President Trump announced
plans to once again
use Guantanamo Bay as a migrant facility.
- We have 30,000 beds in Guantanamo
to detain the worst
criminal illegal aliens
threatening the American people.
And tough.
It's a tough place to get out of.
- After the announcement,
some tent camps were set up,
and several hundred migrants,
mostly from Venezuela,
were held at the base
for a period of time,
but it was only temporary.
And whether these announced plans
will actually be carried
out remains to be seen.
And while Guantanamo made
headlines in the 1990s
as a refugee camp,
in the early 2000s, the
camp becomes the spotlight
for a different challenge that
will define an entire decade.
(tense thoughtful music)
- The United States
military has begun strikes
against Al-Qaeda terrorist training camps
and military installations
of the Taliban regime in Afghanistan.
- [News Reporter] We know
of targets in Kandahar
and Kabul for certain,
some 50 cruise missiles.
- [Host] After the attacks of 2001,
the United States began an
invasion of Afghanistan,
and on the ground, the American military
begins taking prisoners,
except now there is a problem.
Many of the prisoners captured by the US
were suspected to be terrorists,
but the actual amount of evidence
to legally justify detaining
these people was often small.
If they are sent back to the
United States for a trial,
it could be very likely that
they are found not guilty.
And so once again, the American government
turns its eye towards
its previous location
to deal with tricky
situations: Guantanamo Bay.
If a prisoner is sent here,
they can still be imprisoned
by the American military,
but without any of the protections
that being in the United States
would otherwise give them,
such as the right to a fair trial.
And so, almost immediately,
suspected terrorists
are shipped across the world to this base.
- Terrorists who once occupied Afghanistan
now occupy cells at Guantanamo Bay.
(audience applauding)
(gentle contemplative music)
- [Host] Guantanamo Bay
was not well-equipped
to become a terrorist prisoner camp,
and so the decision is made
to use the temporary infrastructure
of an already existing camp, Camp X-Ray,
the same location where Haitian
and Cuban refugees were sent
if they caused issues
during the refugee crisis.
- The heat here is intense,
and the guards say that it's
baking inside the prison cells
with their concrete
floors and wire caging.
- These photographs
showing the first prisoners
being taken to the camp
were taken by the military,
but they had not been published for years.
Only through a New York Times
Freedom of Information Act request,
they became public in 2022.
The prisoners are shackled,
their hands and ears covered.
They are essentially
deprived of their senses.
One soldier plants an American flag
in a prisoner's shackled hands.
And other photos show
the medical facilities
where prisoners are checked.
This photo shows a prisoner facing away
as a guard brings food.
(light pulsing music)
After about four months,
the detainees are moved to
a new permanent location
that is set up at the same place
where the HIV camp used to be
during the refugee crisis in the '90s.
This camp is now called Camp Delta.
Over the coming years, this
camp is continuously expanded
and is further broken down
into several sub-camps,
ranging from low- to
high-security prisons.
A tiered system where the
more compliant prisoner
is moved to a lower-security
camp that has more freedoms,
while the difficult detainees
are kept at higher security.
In the higher-security camps,
detainees are held in
virtual solitary confinement.
They're allowed only two hours
of recreation time each day
in individual pens
with no interaction allowed
with the other prisoners.
(light thoughtful music)
A little further east, also
located directly by the ocean,
Camp Iguana is set up
to house three prisoners
that were below the age of 16.
Though later it was confirmed
that there were other underage
prisoners at Guantanamo
that were not held at Camp Iguana.
This photo shows the
recreation yard at Camp Iguana
facing the sea.
There's something fascinating
about the contrast
between the natural beauty of this place
and the harshness of this prison camp.
With all the different camps,
there isn't a definitive system
that dictates when prisoners
should be moved between them.
There are no trials and no review boards.
(bright soft music)
The American government
claims that the prisoners at Guantanamo
are not protected by the US Constitution,
as they are not on US territory.
But there is still international law
that dictates how a prisoner
of war ought to be treated.
And one of the things prohibited
by the Geneva Conventions
is indefinite imprisonment
without charge or a trial.
And so President Bush begins adopting
a simple use of wordplay
to skirt these restrictions
by labeling the detainees
as enemy combatants
rather than prisoners of war.
Several countries continually call
for the closure of Camp Delta
over human rights abuses,
including the use of torture on detainees.
Eventually, the Bush
administration starts to backtrack.
The government wants to close Camp Delta,
but they can't as long as
there are still prisoners.
Hundreds of detainees are
released or transferred,
but many still remain.
Unless the US is willing to simply release
the remaining prisoners,
which they are not,
there has to be a trial,
but you can't have a
trial without a courtroom,
of which there is none on the base.
And so the plan is made
to build Camp Justice.
Initially, Camp Justice was intended to be
a permanent courthouse
that would've cost around $100 million US.
However, Congress is not
willing to allow such a budget.
Politically, on the list of
things to spend money on,
a courthouse in Guantanamo is
about as unpopular as it gets.
Therefore, the budget is capped
at just 1/10 of the initial
proposal, $10 million.
This isn't near enough to
construct a brand-new courthouse
on a military base detached
from the rest of the country.
And so the plan is reworked,
and instead of a solid building,
portable tents are set up yet
again on the old airfield.
It looks not too dissimilar
to the tents that housed
refugees just a decade earlier.
Within those tents, the
detainees are not given a trial
like they would be entitled to in the US.
Instead, they are military tribunals.
Prisoners often don't have access
to the evidence used against
them to offer a rebuttal.
Decisions don't need to be unanimous,
and many parts of the tribunal
are closed off to the public,
sometimes even to the
defendant's own attorneys.
But over the years, this tent
city has seen very little use.
As of 2025, only eight
men have been convicted
since Camp Justice has been established,
and half of those convictions
have since been overturned.
- I have opposed the president
on spending on climate change,
on torture of prisoners,
on Guantanamo Bay.
- I said repeatedly that I
intend to close Guantanamo,
and I will follow through on that.
- Barack Obama and John McCain said,
"We need to close Guantanamo,"
but we all forgot to ask
the next question: How?
(light thoughtful music)
- Most of the hundreds of
prisoners held in Camp Delta
have instead been transferred
to other countries,
or they have been released with no charges
after being held for years on end.
And as of the making of this video,
only 15 men are remaining.
The cost per prisoner
at the highest-security
federal prisons in the US
is $78,000 per year.
Based on official numbers from 2015,
we know the cost of running
just the prison facility
at Guantanamo Bay,
and based on the current
population of prisoners,
their cost per prisoner at Guantanamo
comes out to a staggering $29 million US.
(tense thoughtful music)
The term "Guantanamo Bay"
is collectively linked
to the War on Terror,
as the camp continues to be
controversial to this day.
But really, this is just
one of many chapters
in the base's history that
all follow one common theme,
as the base is a reflection of
America's uneasy relationship
with the rest of the world.
By wanting to help,
but also wanting to control,
(explosion booms)
By surrounding others,
but yet feeling surrounded.
By offering opportunity
while building fences.
And by defending ideals
while sometimes suspending
them when convenient.
And as a place full of contradictions,
the history of this base holds a mirror
to over a century of
foreign policy decisions.
This is Guantanamo Bay.
(bright chiming music)
The War on Terror didn't just
shape places like Guantanamo;
it shaped an entire generation.
It's one of those topics that's so huge,
you can only really understand it
by looking at all the smaller,
stranger stories that came out of it.
One of my favorite shows
recently is "Mad Kings."
It covers some of the world's
most unhinged dictators
and corrupt leaders.
For example, one episode tells
the absolutely crazy life story of Uday,
one of Saddam Hussein's sons,
who committed thousands
upon thousands of crimes
during his father's reign in power,
a documentary that would
immediately get demonetized
or age-restricted on YouTube,
which is why it was made
exclusively for Nebula.
(computer mouse clicks)
(bright thoughtful music)
Nebula is a streaming
service that I helped build
together with a bunch
of like-minded creators,
because we wanted to make bigger, weirder,
and more meaningful stuff than
what usually fits on YouTube.
It is where I uploaded my 3D short film
about the refugee crisis
and my exclusive series "Under Exposure,"
which covers darker subject matter,
such as one episode
about the Bin Laden raid.
Everything on Nebula is made
by independent creators,
which honestly makes it way more creative
than any other streaming
service I know of,
with documentaries, game shows,
and really incredible film projects.
I'm really excited about what
we're building over on Nebula.
And if you click on my link,
you can try it for free yourself.
And if you like it,
it's just $3 a month
using the annual plan.
And there is also a lifetime plan option,
which is currently
discounted using my link.
Thank you so much for watching this video.